All right, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ח, yud-ches,
חי, chai, and also חודש טוב chodesh tov and other שמח. semeach.
So we pick up at the top of י"ח עמוד א' yud-ches
amud alef and the first order of business is going to be
to finish exploring why the example that רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua gave
of הפה שאסר, peh she-asur, which is this field is your father's
and I purchased it from him, why we gave that example as
opposed to other examples. And it's going to feel for the rest...
for this דף daf that we're somewhere in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
or elsewhere because it's going to bring in other types of discussions
about conceding points and
טוען ונטען to'en v'nitan and making a claim, a claimant and a
respondent and so on. And you might be feeling, as happens sometimes
in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara is getting a little bit
off topic and then we're going to get back to כתובות Kesubos
topics. But I want you to know that for the remainder of
this second פרק, perek, this is the discussion, not necessarily specifically טוען
ונטען, to'en v'nitan, but because we introduced an idea of הפה שאסר
peh she-asur and because the משנה Mishnah sort of then brought in
it from a different, completely different halachic category, this idea of רבי
יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua of somebody saying this field was your father's and
I bought it from him, to continue the next set of משניות
mishnayos in this פרק perek are going to be הפה שאסר peh
she-asur scenarios that are very distant from our original כתובות Kesubos case.
Okay, so we're going to be having a whole exploration of הפה
שאסר peh she-asur types of scenarios in a range of cases, particularly
דיני ממונות dinei mamonos
cases.
Certainly yes, one of the main locations of this discussion of הפה
שאסר. peh she-asur. Okay, so with that in mind, let's pick up
at the top of י"ח עמוד א'. yud-ches amud alef. So it
says like this: דליתני מודה רבי יהושע באומר לחבירו מנה לויתי ממך
ופרעתי לך שהוא נאמן. Daleis nei modeh Rebbi Yehoshua b'omer l'chaveiro mane
livity mimcha u-parati lach she-hu ne'eman.
So why did you give the case of the field and I
bought it from your father? So yesterday we asked why didn't we
say I bought it from you? So we said, well, because we
want to say a חידוש chiddush that חזקה chazakah in the presence
of a son of the father doesn't always work. Okay, so that's
why we said we did I bought it from your father rather
than I bought it from you. But now we're saying why give
the case of a field all together? Why didn't we say a
case of a loan? Why didn't we say somebody goes to a
friend and there's no שטר shtar and he says that hundred dollars
I borrowed from you, I paid you off, and there's no external
evidence that he actually had borrowed the money? So that would be
another good case of הפה שאסר. peh she-asur. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says no, משום דקבעי למתני סיפא mishum d'ka ba'ei l'misni seifa
because remember what we want to do is we want to say
if it's all coming from you and it's הפה שאסר peh she-asur
then you're believed, both parts of your statement are believed, the part
that you borrowed the money and the part that you paid it,
or the part that the father owned the field and the part
that you bought it. But if there are witnesses to the first
part of the statement and you're not just freely offering up all
that information, then your claim that you're exempt is not believed. Right,
everybody remembers that's the structure of the משנה. Mishnah. If there are
witnesses the field belonged to the father, then your claim that you
bought it would not be believed. So the גמרא Gemara is saying
we can't do the same type of a structure when it comes
to an issue of loan. משום דקבעי למתני סיפא mishum d'ka ba'ei
l'misni seifa we want to teach in the end, אם יש עדים
שלוה הימנו, im yeish edim she-lova mimenu, we would have to say
in the end that if there are witnesses that he borrowed the
money והוא אומר פרעתי, v'hu omer parati, אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman, he's
not believed. Now that's reasonable. If there are witnesses you borrowed the
money and you just claim you paid it off, we would imagine
you wouldn't be believed, right? You need to have evidence that you
paid it off or at least a receipt or something. So the
גמרא Gemara says but guess what? That's not true! You actually would
be believed. והא קיימא לן, V'ha kayma lan, we adopt as the
principle, המלוה את חבירו בעדים אינו צריך לפורעו בעדים. ha-malveh es chaveiro
b'edim eino tzarich l'poreo b'edim. That if somebody borrows money with witnesses,
meaning with only witnesses and not a שטר, shtar, you do not
need to pay back with witnesses that you actually, when it comes
time to pay back the money, you don't have to schlep around
and find witnesses to establish proof of that fact, and actually you
can just go ahead and pay back and then you're believed to
claim that you paid back. Now to me and you that doesn't...
yeah, that's pretty darn bad for business. What it would do is
that it would push everybody to write a שטר, shtar, which might
be better, that everything gets documented and that it eliminates all these
various claims and counterclaims. On the other hand, if I'm a potential
loaner or creditor and I have to go ahead and bother writing
a שטר, shtar, I'm going to be reluctant to lend as much
money. We're right now in the whole שמיטה shmittah and הלל Hillel
and what הלל Hillel did in order so that people should not
be reluctant to lend money to the poor, right? And I mean
I already have enough of a disincentive that I can't charge interest
unless I do some work-around there. Right? So you are right, one
really does wonder about
the impacts of this type of a
policy, I mean it's a הלכה, halachah, but sort of the, what
are the societal impacts of this type of a ruling? Now the
other question might be what's the logic behind it? If there's proof
you borrowed, why are you just believed to say you didn't? So
it could be as an idea we're going to introduce later, a
type of an idea like חזקה אין אדם מעיז פניו בפני בעל
חובו.
chazakah ein adam meiz panav bifnei
ba'al chovo. Nobody, we assume that nobody would have the חוצפה, chutzpah,
honest enough certainly, yeah, nobody would have the חוצפה... chutzpah... that somebody
that lent them money and did them this טובה tova to give
a bald-faced lie that I paid back, that they wouldn't say. Okay?
So it's a, okay, so it's interesting again from a purely legal
perspective that that's weighty enough to counteract the fact that there were
witnesses that it was borrowed. Now also know by the way that
this is something that its purpose was to be paid back. It's
not like there were witnesses, you know, that you have a, that
this, that something was yours and then I say it's mine, right?
The whole point of a loan was that it was supposed to
be paid back. So it's sort of, there's a natural sort of
logic to the fact that just because there're witnesses doesn't mean it
wasn't paid back. The next step would be that it would be
paid back and you're telling me that the next step occurred. But
nevertheless, one does have to wonder even if there is this type
of presumption what it might do, you know, that it would be
bad for business.
Nevertheless, that's the הלכה. halacha. So since that's the הלכה, halacha, the
גמרא Gemara says we could not have said that, use this as
an example of פה שאסר. peh she'asar. Sure it's true פה שאסר,
peh she'asar, if you say I borrowed the money and I paid
back you're believed. But it has nothing to do with פה שאסר,
peh she'asar, because even if there were witnesses you borrowed you the
money, you'd be believed to say you paid it back, so it's
not really relevant for our משנה. mishna.
Okay, so what's the same, you know,
logic of, I borrow your whatever it is, right? Yeah. And then
to give it back to me then I say no it's mine.
I mean shouldn't we also say that like, you did me this
favor and let me borrow your car. Right. And then I get
to say it's my car. Like that's also like a level of
חוצפה. chutzpah.
Yeah, that I purchased it from you afterwards.
Whatever it is.
Yeah, but
no, I hear that but that's less because then there's actually a
sort of like direct testimony that it's the same object so it
obviously, you know, it creates more of a presumption that it's not
true as opposed to here there's nothing to see or not see.
But yeah, I mean, you know, the גמרא Gemara very selectively applies
these ideas. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
All right, so that's why we didn't give that example. Then the
גמרא Gemara says like this, וליסני מודה ר' יהושע באומר לחבירו, v'lisni
modeh Rabbi Yehoshua b'omer l'chavero, why don't we give the following example
of פה שאסר? peh she'asar? Rabbi Yehoshua agrees if somebody says to
his friend, מנה לאביך בידי והאכלתי פרס, mane l'avicha b'yadi v'he'achalti pras,
that your father lent me a hundred dollars, that's a hundred dollars
of your father's is by me, meaning he lent me a hundred
dollars is in my hands, and I ate half of it, okay,
which means that I paid back half and I still owe the
other half. Now, you're מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, right. So for anybody
who knows who's learned בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, another related גמרות, Gemarot,
there's an idea that if I, somebody comes to me and says
where's the hundred dollars I lent you, and I say, wow, and
I say, and let's say there're no witnesses independent of our earlier
discussion, and I say I paid you back, or I said I
never borrowed the money, I'm called a כופר הכל, kofer hakol, I
reject everything, and therefore actually I walk away, I don't pay. Okay.
But if however I say yes I did borrow the money but
I paid back half of it, I paid back ninety percent of
it, then I concede half of the claim or a part of
the claim, doesn't exactly, any מקצת, miktzat, any part of it, and
therefore I have to swear about the rest. So actually it's a
little bit crazy, right? There's a, like why would, and the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask like since we're on this discussion of מיגו,
miggo, why doesn't every מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat have a מיגו? miggo?
Right, why are you making me swear on the other half, where
if I really wanted to lie I would say nothing. Okay, so
we'll get to that. But there's the idea that a מודה במקצת
modeh b'miktzat has to swear. Now let's say normally what you require
is a טענה, taina, there's טוען ונטען, toein v'nitan, right, a claimant,
a litigant and a respondent. So let's say there's no טענה. taina.
Let's say I just walk up to somebody and say oh by
the way, you know, I borrowed a hundred dollars from you, you've
totally forgotten about it, but I had paid back fifty and here's
the other fifty. Do I have to swear? You're not making a
claim against me about the rest. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara
question here. Maybe that would be a case where you wouldn't have
to swear because no claim is being made. But as soon as
there are witnesses that I borrowed the hundred dollars, then it would
be like a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat.
And then you didn't claim it but the
witnesses said yeah you really borrowed it. The witnesses testified that I
borrowed the hundred dollars and I'm conceding fifty. That would be a
case that I would have to swear. Okay, so that would be
a case that would fit our structure. When I completely sort of
offer up all the information I'm exempt, and when I don't, and
when witnesses establish the first part of it I, I'm, you know,
I have to address the second part. So let's take a look.
So why don't we say the case, וליסני מודה ר' יהושע באומר
לחבירו מנה לאביך בידי, v'lisni modeh Rabbi Yehoshua b'omer l'chavero mane l'avicha
b'yadi, I borrowed a hundred dollars from your father, והאכלתי פרס, v'he'achalti
pras, and I consumed half of it, meaning, meaning I still owe
you half, שנאמן, she'ne'eman,
that he's believed when he says both parts of the statement. But
if there are witnesses on the first part, then presumably he would
not be believed. So the גמרא Gemara says
he would not be believed
that he paid back half. He'd have to swear. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says אליבא דמאן. aliba d'man.
According to whom are you asking this? Because we're going to see
it's a debate of תנאים tana'im what would happen in that case
when witnesses testify to the first half. אי אליבא דרבנן, ei aliba
d'rabanan, if it's according to the rabbis, הא משיב אבידה הוי. ha
meishiv aveida havei.
It's like a guy that returns a lost object. You're not going
to have to make an oath on something
that you didn't have to sort of. to begin with and it
was seen as totally something that you gave back on your goodwill.
I mean obviously כעין מיגו. k'ein miggo.
Right, it's a כעין מיגו, k'ein miggo, essentially it is a מיגו.
miggo. That's the way תוספות Tosafos frames it. Okay, רש"י Rashi tries
to fit it into another תקנה, takana, another הלכה halacha of משיב
אבידה, meshiv aveida, but תוספות's Tosafos's point is that the word משיב
אבידה meshiv aveida here is really being used more like metaphorically. And
what it means is, you know, think about the case where I
come in, I return your lost object. Charlie, I found your wallet
on the street and it had a hundred dollars in it, and
you said, "What? It was two hundred dollars when I lost it!
You have to swear that you didn't take the other hundred dollars!"
So obviously we cannot have people demand that people swear in that
case, right, because they'd never return anything. Okay, so that's like, that's
like the public policy sort of reason to say משיב אבידה meshiv
aveida doesn't have to. But using that as a metaphor, the basic
point is, is that if you offer up information which, you know,
like we wouldn't have sort of known otherwise, and you easily could
have just denied the whole thing or not done anything, gotten out
of it, right, then we're not going to make you swear, which
is a type of a מיגו. miggo. מיגו miggo that you could
have not done any of this, you're going to get out of
it. Okay, so that's the concept of משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. So
let's take a look. So אי
אליבא דרבנן, ei aliba d'rabbanan, הא אמי משיב אבידה הוי, ha ami
meshiv aveida havei, he's a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. And presumably therefore
even if, again there's a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
exactly how to read this, I'll read it תוספות's Tosafos's way, even
if there are witnesses that he borrowed the hundred dollars, because he's
not dealing with the person he borrowed the money from, but the
person's son, there's an assumption that the son has no idea what
his father's business was and I can easily lie to the son.
And therefore since I could easily lie to the son and I
have no compunctions denying the whole thing if I wanted to lie,
right, so therefore any admission is a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. And
therefore I should always be out of making a שבועה, shvua, even
if there are witnesses. Okay, now does everybody again understand, I'm going
to sort of tell you what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say in a minute, but I'll just, you know, but I'm saying
it now to help structure it because you could ask that any
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas is a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. Michael says
"where's my hundred dollars?", I say "I concede fifty." Why am I
not a משיב אבידה? meshiv aveida? I could have said nothing, I
was generous enough to concede fifty. No. I'm not a משיב אבידה
meshiv aveida because he's coming to me with a claim, he was
the guy that lent money to me, and there I would not
be prepared to deny it all. Okay, that's the idea that I'm
not מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. me'iz panav bifnei ba'al chovo. I
don't have the חוצפה chutzpa to deny it all to the guy
that lent me the money.
But you could deny half of it?
Well, we'll get to that. But yes.
Yes. So therefore, for the person who actually lent me the money,
I'm not just oh out of the generosity of my heart I'm
conceding it. Okay, if I really wanted to lie, even if I
wanted to lie I would not be prepared to deny it all.
So we're not I'm not a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. But if
it's the guy's son, and the guy who didn't know the father's
business, if I really wanted to lie I would have absolutely no
problem just saying "I don't owe you anything."
Right. And therefore any admission is a type of a משיב אבידה,
meshiv aveida, means anytime it's always a מיגו miggo that I could
have easily denied it all. Okay, so that's what the רבנן Rabbanan
say. And therefore even if there are witnesses that I borrowed the
money, right, remember even if there are witnesses that I borrowed, I'm
believed to say that I paid it all off, we just established
that. The גמרא Gemara very smartly introduced that first. So we've established
that even with witnesses that I borrowed, I'm believed to say I
paid it all off. So if it's the son, I have no
compunction if I wanted to lie even with witnesses I would say
I paid it off. And therefore when I say half, I also
don't have to pay. So therefore it would not fit in the
structure of the משנה. Mishna. The structure of the משנה Mishna is
if there are witnesses to the first part, I have to pay
or I have to take a שבועה. shvua. Here even if there
are witnesses to the first part I borrowed money, once I say
I paid half I or I paid nothing, either way I'd be
believed. Okay, wait let me just finish this. That's the חכמים. Chachamim.
אי אליבא דרבנן ei aliba d'rabbanan אמר משיב אבידה הוי. amar meshiv
aveida havei. אי אליבא דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
ei aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, according to Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, אמר שבועה בעי, amar
shvua ba'ei, he says that you do have to take a שבועה.
shvua. דתניא, dtanya, we turned a בריתא, Beraisa, but he says he
has to take a שבועה shvua even without witnesses. So they go
to opposite extremes. Okay, דתניא, dtanya, we turned a בריתא, Beraisa, רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer פעמים שאדם נשבע
על טענת עצמו. pe'amim she'adam nishba al ta'anas atzmo. Sometimes a person
will have to take an oath even on a claim his own
claim, meaning even on something that he himself offered up. He was
not responding to a claim from the other party. Okay, basically פה
שאסר. peh she'asar. Okay, כיצד? keitzad? How is that possible? מנה לאביך
בידי והאכלתי פרס, maneh l'avicha b'yadi v'he'echalti pras, הרי זה נשבע. harei
zeh nishba.
If somebody says "I borrowed a hundred dollars from your father and
I ate half," he still has to take an oath. Okay, וזהו
שנשבע על טענת עצמו, v'zehu she'nishba al ta'anas atzmo, he's doing it
even though he's like a total, you know, פה שאסר, peh she'asar,
he's doing it he's offering up all the information, there's no claim
being made against him. וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say,
אינו אלא כמשיב אבידה ופטור. eino ela k'meshiv aveida u'patur. He's only
a generous guy, he's conceding something, he's like a משיב אבידה, meshiv
aveida, he's exempt. So basically what it says is, now it's not
spelled out what the גמרא Gemara is assuming about this, but what
the גמרא Gemara is assuming is that they argue at the extremes.
Meaning רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov which is pretty
clear, he's saying that even if there's no claim against him, even
if he's a פה שאסר, peh she'asar, he still has to make
a שבועה. shvua. So that couldn't fit in the משנה Mishna because
the whole point of the משנה Mishna is that. or he's exempt,
and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says that no,
in this case of פה שאסר Peh she-asar he's actually liable. We'll
find out why in a minute, but that's what רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says. And the חכמים Chachamim couldn't say
this case, because they hold that even when there are עדים, edim,
even when there is a claim by the son and that there
are עדים edim against you, you're believed because of משיב אבידה Meshiv
Aveidah and because of a מיגו. migo. Okay, so everybody gets the
case? That's why we don't have it in the משנה. Mishnah. The
case in the משנה Mishnah is when you offer it all up
you're exempt, when there are עדים edim to the first part you're
חייב. chayav. And here it's saying it doesn't work according to either
position. According to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov when
you offer it all up you're still חייב, chayav, and according to
the חכמים Chachamim even when there are עדים, edim, you're still exempt.
Okay, and now what we have to do is we have to
figure out, we explained why according to the חכמים Chachamim you're exempt,
the logic of משיב אבידה Meshiv Aveidah and you have no compunction
to lie completely to the son and deny it all. What we
haven't explained is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov why
you're חייב chayav if there's no claim against you. Why would you
ever be חייב chayav if there's no claim, whatever happened to פה
שאסר? Peh she-asar? Yes, רבי דוב, Rabbi Dov, you had a question.
I just want to make sure this is like a simple question.
Is the גמרא Gemara trying to figure out if the סיפא seifa
of the משנה Mishnah is also part of רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua
statement or is it?
No, it's I know, I know. Yeah, no, it's assuming it's part
of רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua statement. It's just saying that why did
he give an example of a field and not give an example
and not give another example? Not give an example of borrowing money?
What is unique about this example, the field? What it does is
it offers the גמרא Gemara an opportunity, whether the גמרא Gemara sincerely
is wondering why it did not he didn't give another example, because
I bet I'll bet you a million dollars if he'd given the
example of borrowing money, we'd say why didn't he give an example
about the field?
So, anyway, right. So, whether the גמרא Gemara sincerely wonders why he
didn't give another example or whether the גמרא Gemara actually just is
using this as an opportunity to explore, you know, this same logic
in other cases, okay, but that's what we're doing. We're looking at
parallel cases of פה שאסר Peh she-asar with the same exactly. Okay.
So now let's look at רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov. So we got the חכמים, Chachamim, we understand why you're exempt,
basically a type of מיגו, migo, a משיב אבידה, Meshiv Aveidah, even
when there are witnesses. But why according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov are you חייב chayav if it's a what
do you call it, are you חייב chayav if it's even if
you're even if you're
offering up all the information? So the גמרא Gemara asks that question.
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב לית ליה משיב אבידה פטור? Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov leis lei Meshiv Aveidah patur? Doesn't he hold of משיב אבידה,
Meshiv Aveidah, which again the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, that's just
a way of expressing the מיגו migo that you have here, a
way of saying in this case פה שאסר, Peh she-asar, you're offering
up all the information, you're coming forth and saying I owe you
fifty dollars. So doesn't he agree you'd be exempt from a שבועה
shvua because you could have said nothing? So אמר רב בטענו קטן.
Amar Rav be-ta'ano katan. We don't really mean טענת עצמו. ta'anat atzmo.
We mean that the that the guy,
it's like there's no opposite טענה ta'ana because the person that's pressing
the charge is a קטן. katan. And therefore normally the charge of
a קטן katan doesn't have weight, so we're calling it טענת עצמו.
ta'anat atzmo. But the reality is that you're not a משיב אבידה
Meshiv Aveidah because presumably he he says you would not be prepared
to lie to the son the same way you're not prepared to
lie to the father fully, you're not prepared to lie to the
son. And therefore you do have to pay. So, right, everybody gets
it? רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says that when
you say I borrowed fifty dollars a hundred from your father I
paid back half, that that's no different than saying to the guy
itself I borrowed a hundred dollars from you and paid back half.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying because you are the same way
you're not prepared to totally lie to the guy, you're not prepared
to totally lie to the son. And the same way you have
to make a שבועה shvua in the case of the guy himself,
you have to make a שבועה shvua to the son. The only
problem is that even with the guy himself, you only make a
שבועה shvua when the guy comes with a claim against you. And
here רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov said even if
you're טענת עצמו, ta'anat atzmo, even if you're offering up all the
information yourself. So we didn't literally mean טענת עצמו. ta'anat atzmo. The
there's a claim against you here too. It's just the claim of
the son, it's a claim of a
קטן. katan.
As if the father was there himself.
Well, that's true well that's true also, but the reason the גמרא
Gemara picked קטן katan is because that allows for the language of
טענת עצמו. ta'anat atzmo. Of course the גמרא Gemara is going to
say that you so but the whole point that קטן katan is
like is not normally a legitimate claim gets us back to our
original question. והאמר מר אין נשבעין על טענת חרש שוטה וקטן. Ve-ha-amar
mar ein nishba'in al ta'anat cheresh shoteh ve-katan. You don't take a
שבועה shvua against a claim from a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh
ve-katan. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, no, מאי קטן? mai katan?
We don't literally mean minor. We mean
גדול. gadol.
You gotta love the גמרא. Gemara.
מאי קטן? גדול. mai katan gadol. Okay, so מאי קטן mai katan?
גדול. gadol. ואמאי קרי ליה קטן? Ve-amai karei lei katan? Why is
he called a minor? משום דלגבי מילי דאביב קטן הוא. mishum de-legabei
milei de-aviv katan hu.
Because he's a minor, he's unknowledgeable when it comes to his father's
matters. So what he means is that basically the debate is that
the חכמים Chachamim say once you're dealing with the son and the
guy you didn't borrow the money from, you're prepared to totally lie.
So anything you admit to is a משיב אבידה Meshiv Aveidah and
you don't have to take a שבועה. shvua. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says you're not prepared to lie to the
son the same way you're not prepared to lie to the father,
or not totally, you're not prepared to totally deny it, and therefore
you still have to take a שבועה. shvua. The only problem is
though wait a minute the only problem though is is that the
גמרא Gemara is still calling it like you know טענת עצמו ta'anat
atzmo and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב's Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov whole point
is that you're not prepared to lie to the son, that the
son's claim against you has the same weight that the father's claim
against you has. So why are we calling it טענת עצמו? ta'anat
atzmo? So תוספות Tosafot has a very ingenious answer. תוספות Tosafot says
because the חכמים Chachamim consider it to be that the claim has
no weight. Meaning the חכמים Chachamim say you're prepared to lie to
the son, his claim against you has no weight in your mind,
and therefore, you know, therefore you're always believed, you're a משיב אבידה
meshiv aveida because you would completely be prepared to, you know, to
deny it. So רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov is
saying back, that that you consider to be טענת עצמו ta'anat atzmo
in your mind חכמים, Chachamim, you think that the son's claim has
no weight and it's like the guy's just offering up the information
on his own, I disagree with you. I actually think the son's
claim does have weight and it's a normal case of מודה במקצת
modeh b'miktzat and he takes a שבועה. shvua. So that the reason
we're calling it טענת עצמו ta'anat atzmo is not because רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov thinks it's טענת עצמו, ta'anat atzmo,
that's exactly what they're debating. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov thinks that the son's claim has weight and it's like dealing
with the father. But he says what you think is טענת עצמו,
ta'anat atzmo, I think that the guy still takes a
שבועה. shvua. But if it really was טענת עצמו, ta'anat atzmo, of
course you wouldn't, because you need a טענה ta'ana and you'd be
a משיב אבידה meshiv aveida and you'd be a מיגו migo and
you'd have all of that. פשט pshat also, you'd have all of
that.
And also everyone agrees that if it really was a קטן, katan,
then they wouldn't...
exactly.
Okay, so we're saying קטן דגדול katan d'gadol is called the קטן
katan because it's like
George Junior.
Right, exactly.
In other words, he could be a major but he's just junior.
There you go. Okay, so now we've got that their debate is,
their debate is whether the claim of the son has weight as
a normal claim. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says
yes and therefore you take a שבועה shvua even if there are
no עדים, eidim, if you admit half, and the חכמים Chachamim say
no, it has no weight of a טענה ta'ana and because you're
not prepared to lie to the
son, you're prepared to lie to the son and therefore even with
עדים eidim you'd be believed because you're just a מיגו migo and
a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, and also all
agree that if you're כופר הכל, kofer hakol, yes, that's always true.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי
הכי
I
hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's the case, טענת עצמו? ta'anat
atzmo? טענת אחרים היא! ta'anat acherim hi! It is the טענה ta'ana
of somebody else. The son is pressing the charges, I mean, the
son is making the claim. גמרא Gemara says, no. טענת אחרים והודאת
עצמו. ta'anat acherim v'hoda'at atzmo. Fine, other people are making the son
is making a claim against you but it's your admission, so that's
why we're calling it טענת עצמו. ta'anat atzmo. Your own sort of
claim, your claim against yourself. So the גמרא Gemara says, כולה טענה
טענת אחרים והודאת עצמו נינהו! Kula ta'ana ta'anat acherim v'hoda'at atzmo ninhu!
Anytime you have a court case, somebody else is making a claim
against you and you're conceding whatever you're conceding. So why again we're
back to why does רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
call it טענת עצמו, ta'anat atzmo, your claim against yourself, if here
really you are responding to the claim that the son is making?
So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא הכא בדרבה קמיפלגי. Ella hacha b'd'Rabba kamifligi. So
really they're debating רבה. Rabba. And anyway, this is just going to
spell out the logic of why a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat takes
a שבועה shvua and why he would not take a שבועה shvua
here according to the חכמים. Chachamim. So let's take a look. דאמר
רבה, D'amar Rabba, רבה Rabba says, מפני מה אמרה תורה מודה במקצת
ישבע. mipnei mah amrah torah modeh b'miktzat yishava.
Why does the תורה Torah say that if you concede half you
have to take a שבועה? shvua? Meaning תוספות's Tosafot question is not
that it says this is not like we're דרשינן טעמא דקרא. darshinan
ta'ama d'kra. Okay, this is we have actually a legal question here.
Why when you concede half do you have to take a שבועה?
shvua? Why isn't it always a מיגו migo that you could have
denied everything? Okay, yes. So why isn't it just a מיגו? migo?
So the reason is
חזקה אין אדם מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. chazakah ein adam meiz
panav bifnei ba'al chovo. No, you're not prepared to deny everything. You're
not so brazen that you actually would completely deny the whole debt.
You're brazen enough to deny half but not the whole thing. We'll
see why deny half. But anyway, you don't have a מיגו. migo.
What? So חזקה chazakah means a lot of different things. חזקה chazakah
does not just mean status quo. חזקה chazakah means, right, it's like
we can
determine that this is an established way, like an established pattern that
people do, an established
aspect of human nature, just like the way people operate, the way
society operates, and therefore we can make assumptions based on it. Okay,
yes.
So people are so the assumption here is that someone would be
willing to steal
part of someone...
Yes, well we're going to finish spelling that out, correct. Okay, well
let's let the גמרא Gemara finish spelling that out. So therefore you
don't have a מיגו migo because a מיגו migo is I could
have easily have done the other thing. You couldn't have easily done
the other thing. You're not prepared to deny the whole thing. Okay.
והאי בכולי בעי דליכפריה. V'hai b'chulei ba'i d'lichtre.
So you really, if you were really lying, is the point, or
the guy who's a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat who we suspect him
of lying, we're saying you know what, he really would have wanted
to deny the whole thing. והאי דלא כפריה ליה, V'hai d'lo kafrei
lei, and why didn't he deny the whole thing? משום דאין אדם
מעיז פניו בפניו הוא. mishum d'ein adam meiz panav b'fanav hu. Because
people don't have that degree of חוצפה. chutzpah. This is why we're
saying that the מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat has to swear because basically
we're saying like, okay, you know, we suspect him of lying but
he doesn't have a מיגו. migo. migo because even if he were
lying he wouldn't have, he wasn't prepared to deny the whole thing,
he only admitted to half of it, and therefore we're going to
have him make a שבועה shvuah in order to get him to
admit, okay? Now, ובכולי בעי דלודי ליה ubkulei ba'ei d'lodei lei and
we're going to now go to the opposite, swing the pendulum the
opposite way. So really, if he's not prepared to lie, he really
doesn't even want to lie about half of it, right? If he's
not prepared to lie about the whole, or you know, then he's
not necessarily because he's honest, or just because he's a little bit
ashamed, it doesn't really matter. Okay, but he really, the same way
he really wouldn't deny the whole thing, he really doesn't want to
deny even part of it, okay? But והאי דלא אודי ליה v'hai
d'lo odei lei so then why not admit it if you're so
ashamed to lie even for part of it? כי היכי דלישתמיט ליה
ki heichi d'lishtamit lei so
in order to buy some time. וסבר עד דהוו לי זוזי פרענא
ליה v'savar ad d'havu li zuzie parana lei
that I need to buy some time and I'll wait to get
money and pay the guy back. I mean this really does happen,
right? You know, people really, they might sincerely want to pay it
back but you know, they don't have the money when it's due
and they make up lies or whatever in order to you know,
but they're still intending to pay it back. Okay, so therefore, that's
how we understand the psychology of this guy and why he doesn't
have a מיגו. migo. Now תוספות Tosafot asks, like, why did we
have to say the whole second part? Oh, he really wants to
admit the whole thing, but he's buying time? Just say he's not
prepared to deny the whole, he's prepared to deny half. So there's
two ways of explaining why the גמרא Gemara needed the second part.
One way of explaining it is that the גמרא'ס Gemara's basically answers,
there's a principle in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, there's a question in
בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, do we say חשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא? chashid
amamona chashid ashvuata?
If a person is prepared to steal, he's prepared to take a
false oath. Or do we say no, false oath is much more
weighty for people, even people that would get out of their monetary
obligations wouldn't take a false oath. So if we say חשיד אממונא
חשיד אשבועתא, chashid amamona chashid ashvuata, how do we ever think that
a שבועה shvuah will make anybody admit? Because if you're lying, you'll
also take a false oath. So if that's true, we have to
always explain that the oath only works in ways in which you're
not fully trying to steal the money. You're only like, you
know, delay tactics, you've rationalized it, you're not blatantly stealing the money.
And if it's some type of a rationalization and delay tactic, then
a שבועה shvuah will work. So that's one way of understanding this
גמרא. Gemara. If this guy's really lying, how is the שבועה shvuah
going to do any good? He'll just take a false oath. No,
he's not really, he's not really חשיד אממונא, chashid amamona, he's not
really trying to get out of his debt. That's one way of
explaining this גמרא. Gemara. The other way, maybe the simpler way is
what תוספות Tosafot says, is what, it is, if you think that
his denying the whole thing, you know, you assume that it's true
because he wouldn't be brazen enough to deny it if he doesn't,
if he really owed the money, then we should apply the same
logic to the half that he's denying. He wouldn't be brazen enough
to deny half of it, right? So why doesn't he get out
of taking the oath for the half that he's denying? Because he
wouldn't be brazen. It says no, actually half of it he would
be brazen enough, okay? Because he's not so brazen, because once you
admit to the guy that you did borrow the money, the guy
doesn't, and exactly, you feel it's in person, you feel that the
guy is going to maybe you know, make, maybe think that you
made a mistake. You're already, when you're already conceding part of it
to the guy, you actually are more prepared to deny the other
half, and therefore you're not believed on that half that you're denying,
and therefore you have to take a שבועה, shvuah, okay? So that's
the whole logic of מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, basically the explanation I
told you earlier that why you don't have a מיגו migo by
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat because you're not prepared to deny the whole
thing. And now let's see how that plays out in terms of
the issue of the son, okay? ורחמנא אמר v'Rachmana amar and the
Torah says רמי שבועה עליה remi shvuah alei put a שבועה shvuah
on him כי היכי דלודי בכולי ki heichi d'lodei b'kulei to get
him to admit the whole thing. So now here's how that plays
out in terms of this debate about the son. רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב סבר Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov savar לא שנא בו ולא שנא
בבנו lo shna bo v'lo shna b'vno אינו מעיז. eino me'iz. You're
not, the same way you're not prepared to lie to him and
deny the whole thing, you're not prepared to deny to the son.
So the claim that the son has against you is just like
the claim of the father, and you don't have any מיגו migo
because you're not prepared to lie. So when you admit the half,
you're a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat and you have to take the
שבועה, shvuah, and you can't say מיגו migo I could have denied
the whole thing. Okay, וזהו כעין משיב אבידה הוא. v'zehu k'ein meshiv
aveidah hu. You're not being generous in admitting anything, you're, you were,
you're not prepared to deny the whole thing. ורבנן סברי v'Rabbanan savri
the Rabbis hold, בו הוא דאינו מעיז, bo hu d'eino me'iz, he's
not going to be brazen about, to the guy himself he borrowed
the money from, אבל בבנו מעיז, aval b'vno me'iz, but by the
son he is prepared to. So any, in any case, if I
really wanted to lie, I would totally be prepared to deny the
whole thing. And therefore, וכיון דלא העיז v'keivan d'lo he'iz and if
I'm not going to be brazen and deny the whole thing, משיב
אבידה הוא. meshiv aveidah hu. So I am, me, you know, I
am just giving up the money that I didn't have to admit
to because I could have easily had denied the whole thing. That's
basically the פשטא דסבר. pshata d'savar. I didn't have to admit to
anything here, I could have denied the whole thing, there was nothing
stopping me from denying the whole thing. Even if there are witnesses
I borrowed the money, there's nothing stopping me from denying the whole
thing. And therefore, I am believed when I say that I paid
up half. Whereas רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says
no, it's just like the father and you're not believed, it's the
classic case of a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. So according to... the
חכמים Chachamim we couldn't give this case in the משנה Mishnah because
according to the חכמים Chachamim you're believed even when there are witnesses
if all you're doing is responding to the son and according to
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov we couldn't give this
case because according to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov
you are you are not believed even when you admit the whole
thing if you're responding to the claim of the son. The claim
of the son is a real claim. The reason it's called טענת
עצמו tanas atzmo is because the חכמים Chachamim think it's not a
טענה. tana. But he points out it is a real טענה tana
and therefore you are not believed you still have to take a
שבועה. shevuah. Yes. I sort of lost the thread of the question
of why the case of the שדה sadeh is introduced in the
משנה Mishnah and not the case of a loan. Because I just
repeated that. Because the case of the loan, the structure of the
משנה Mishnah is if you concede the whole thing then if you
offer up all the information פה שאסר peh she-asar you're exempt but
if there are witnesses for the first half you're חייב. chayav. Whereas
so according to the חכמים Chachamim it doesn't work because according to
the חכמים Chachamim even if there are witnesses for the first half
you're exempt and according to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov it doesn't work because even if you concede the whole thing
you're still going to be חייב. chayav. In this case why was
the same logic applied to the case of real estate? Because in
the case of real estate you just don't have the whole משיב
אבידה meshiv aveidah type of a thing. You're not giving back half.
We don't have this whole idea of חזקה אין אדם מעיז, chazakah
ein adam meiz, we don't have the whole same dynamic. It's there,
the whole thing is there. If I say that I bought the
field off your father but you didn't know there's no evidence that
it's your father's of course I'm believed I didn't have to say
anything. And if I say and if there are witnesses that it
was your father's then of course I'm not believed because of תנא
תנא היא. tanna tanna hi. Yeah exactly. I mean you could say
חזקה hazakah whatever the same dynamic doesn't work. Is there a reason
why the משנה Mishnah sometimes says the תנא קמא tanna kamma and
sometimes says the רבנן? rabbanan? Oh I don't know. I don't. Okay
but it is the same. Yeah there's no reason why it changes.
Okay you paid me back the dollar fifty? Yeah right. Okay משנה.
Mishnah. So now as I said don't think that we are digressing
when we discuss that whole thing because the whole the topic for
this פרק perek is or for a good part of this פרק
perek is
פה שאסר peh she-asar in a range of different applications. So let's
look at the next application. העדים שאמרו כתב ידינו הוא זה אבל
אנוסים היינו קטנים היינו פסולי עדות היינו הרי אלו נאמנים. Ha-edim she-amru
kesav yadeinu hu zeh aval anusim hayinu ketanim hayinu pesulei edus hayinu
harei elu ne-emanim.
So you have a document that has signatures and the signatures are
not verified. Okay now what you would have to do in court
is I bring a document that has signatures the court is going
to actually either bring in the people who actually signed it and
says are these your signatures or bring in witnesses who recognize who
recognize it and can testify to your signature or a document that's
already been attested to and that
has the seal of בית דין beis din on it because it
went through that
process and compare the signatures. Okay yeah everybody good? It's sort of
like when you sign the back of your credit card and then
you sign the receipt and they compare it and so on. Also
when you go to the notary. Okay there you go that's maybe
a better example.
Okay so that's
called קיום שטרות kiyum shtarot establishing the signatures on a document. Until
that's happened it's not like the שטר shtar is not considered to
be valid or at and it's not considered like the testimony in
the שטר shtar
is being presented
like the witnesses are testifying.
Okay so here you have
a non-validated שטר shtar and the witnesses come and say
yes that is our signature but the testimony actually is is not
binding it's not a good שטר. shtar.
Why is it not a good שטר? shtar? It's not a good
שטר shtar because when we signed it we were קטנים ketanim or
when we signed
it we actually were related to
one of the people.
Okay or when we
signed it it's because the guy had a gun to our head
and he said you better sign it or I'm going to kill
you okay and therefore we signed it even though it was even
though it was false. In the first two cases the transaction never
occurred. In the first two cases the transaction occurred you know but
it was not a good שטר shtar because we were פסול. pasul.
In the last case the transaction never occurred we were just forced
to sign it. So basically in the same act that they are
doing notice it's a פה שאסר peh she-asar of validating the שטר
shtar they're saying that the שטר shtar is invalid. Okay so is
that so the משנה Mishnah says okay that's a פה שאסר peh
she-asar it's like they never validated the שטר. shtar. Now here I
want to stop and say something important about the פה שאסר peh
she-asar logic because there's two ways of explaining פה שאסר peh she-asar
okay you figure out the ways. I come let's go back to
the field case. Yes this field was your father's and I bought
it from him. Okay so so we're going to say פה שאסר
פה שהתיר. peh she-asar peh she-hitir. That can mean one of two
things. It could either mean that just like
we believe the first
part of the statement we believe the second part of the statement
or what's the alternative? Don't believe any part of the statement right?
Saying look those two claims neutralize themselves so really it is immaterial
whether we believe you or not you know we won't register the
claim altogether you didn't say anything they completely neutralize themselves. Alright now
what difference does it make if you say we believe both or
we believe neither? The difference it makes is is that if another
factor gets triggered because we believed one part of the statement. So
if the witnesses come in and say yes this is our signature
but it's we were אנוסים anusim or קטנים ketanim as soon as
they say it's their signature that might be seen as a validating
of the שטר. shtar. Once it's a validating of the שטר shtar
we actually have now The difference it makes is that if another
factor gets triggered because we believed one part of the statement. So
if the witnesses come in and say, yes, this is our signature,
but we were אנוסים anusim or קטנים, ktanim, as soon as they
say it's their signature, that might be seen as a validating of
the שטר. shtar. Once it's a validating of the שטר, shtar, we
actually have now in our presence testimony that something occurred. And now
when you're trying to say, oh, and by the way, though we
were קטנים, ktanim, that might not work to neutralize it, because because
your the first half of your statement didn't remain just your statement
and then the second half is also believed. What happened is the
first half of your statement triggered the validity of the שטר, shtar,
and the שטר shtar now is עדות edut and testimony, and that's
and that testimony, the second part of your statement might not be
weighty enough to counter. You know it doesn't make any sense too?
I understand formalistically, I understand how you play that. Right.
So my point is, well, okay, but the משנה mishna actually says
that it does work in this case. And that's why תוספות tosafot
says that part of this a part of what's going what we
see here is the פה שאסר peh she'asar in the משנה, mishna,
the גמרא gemara might not might not keep to it. But the
פה שאסר peh she'asar in the משנה mishna basically means it's like
they didn't do anything. It's not like they were מקיים mekayem the
שטר shtar and then they invalidated it. Because if they were מקיים
mekayem and they invalidated it, they wouldn't be able to invalidate it.
They'd already triggered its validity. Okay. So what they did was is
they didn't even it's not even like they were מקיים mekayem it.
If in the same statement that it was, yes it's our signatures,
but we were you know we were פסול, pasul, so that doesn't
count as a validation of the שטר shtar and they didn't do
anything. Okay. And that's so much to the point that רש״י rashi
even says that they're saying it תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur.
Okay. So it's really like, you know, the two parts of the
statement. It's really like the statement at the end of the day
didn't say anything. You basically said nothing. Okay. Like מסכת קידושין? masechet
kiddushin? No. I'm not going to make any sense. Okay. Anyway, הרי
אלו נאמנים. harei elu ne'emanim. ואם יש עדים שכתב ידם או שכתב
ידם יוצא ממקום אחר, ve'im yesh edim shektav yadam o shektav yadam
yotze mimakom acher, but if other people testify that it's their signature
or we have a validated document that we compare it to and
we see that it's their signature, then אינם נאמנים, einam ne'emanim, then
it's already a valid שטר shtar and they're not believed because again
it's not a פה שאסר. peh she'asar. The first half of the
statement has already been established. Okay. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. Now we're going to have some fun, okay, because now
we're going to look at this whole issue about the nature of
testimony in a שטר. shtar. אמר רמי בר חמא, amar rami bar
chama, לא שנו, lo shanu, when it's when it says that they're
not believed if they say basically that they you know if the
שטר shtar has already been established and they say that they were
forced to sign it, they're not believed. That that's only true that
they're not believed אלא שאמרו אנוסים היינו מחמת ממון. ela she'amru anusim
hayinu machmat mamon. If they say basically we were forced because of
money. What does forced because of money mean? Either that they were
bribed, which is not really forced at all, or it means that
the guy basically said, if you don't sign this שטר, shtar, I'm
going to burn your house down. And in those cases, because signing
a שטר shtar is considered as bearing false testimony, right, it's considered
an act of being עדות שקר, edut sheker, so therefore, you know,
you're not as if somebody that's an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa and
you're not supposed to do an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa even
you know even if your even if your money is at risk,
only if like your life is at risk. Okay. So then they're
actually saying that what they did is that they actually were רשעים
resha'im when they signed it, okay, because they were being עדות שקר.
edut sheker. Okay. Then in אבל, aval, so therefore in that case,
then they're not believed. Okay. Because we're not going to assume, take
your testimony that you were a רשע. rasha. Now interestingly, when you
say that you're a קטן, katan, or when you say that you
were a קרוב, karov, okay, you're not saying you were a רשע.
rasha. You might be saying I shouldn't have signed the document, but
being a קטן katan or a קרוב karov is not a רשע.
rasha. Being being like giving bearing false testimony, right, that is being
a רשע. rasha. So therefore that's why you're not believed when
the שטר shtar has already been established.
אבל אנוסים היינו מחמת נפשות, aval anusim hayinu machmat nefashot, if they
but if they're saying a guy had a gun to our head,
הרי אלו נאמנים. harei elu ne'emanim. They are believed. Now that is
a very strange statement because if the document has already been validated
through other people, why would they be believed to say that we
were we signed it falsely because the guy had a gun to
our head? So here's the reason why. Because a document is testimony.
But if both of the witnesses are saying, we actually were forced
to sign this false document, the guy had a gun to our
head, guess what the what happens? What's the status of the words
that they're saying too? They're two people and they are also bearing
witness. They are also testifying. So he's basically saying, okay, so you
have now you've the testimony of the שטר. shtar. That was validated
because you've already got other people to testify to the signatures. It's
a validated שטר. shtar. It's testifying that the loan took place. Now
you have two witnesses coming in and saying the loan didn't take
place and we were forced to sign it. So why so they
would be believed. The only reason they're not believed is if they
said the loan didn't take place because of the because the guy
was threatening to burn our house down. Then we're saying, well then
you're basically telling me that you're a רשע rasha because you bore
false testimony, you know, out of a threat of money. So if
you're telling me you're a רשע, rasha, I reject everything you're saying.
Okay. That's why you wouldn't be believed. But if you actually say
that we had no choice, he had a gun to our head,
then then the גמרא gemara is saying then you are believed, you're
testifying against. against your other testimony and you're believed basically. So now
we get to an issue about retracting your earlier testimony. If only
one of them did it then he wouldn't be believed. If only
one did it he would not be believed. But since it's two
they're also offering testimony. So he's saying what's the motivation that they
both say this because they know by saying that they're going to
get off. They're not getting off. It's about a שטר shtar against
somebody else. ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon find a document that you
borrowed a hundred dollars from מיכאל, Michael, okay? So they're not on
the line. They're just saying that document that we signed, it's because
דוד David had a gun to our head, it never happened, the
loan didn't take place. So right now they're bearing testimony that there
was no loan. Okay. So he's saying you are believed actually. You're
also giving testimony. Alright? You don't believe to make myself like תשובה?
teshuva? I'm making myself a רשע, rasha, oh God, I sinned this?
No, you know what, you work that out with Scott. But basically
legally if you said that you signed it because of money or
because of threat of losing money, then you're telling us you're a
רשע. rasha. Anyway, what do I care? Work that out with Scott.
Okay. הרי אלו נאמנים. harei elu ne'emanim. אמר ליה רבא, amar lei
Rava, said רבא, Rava, one minute. כל כמיניה? kol kimeineh? Is he,
are they believed at all when they come with their second claim,
even if they're two people and they're bearing witness? כיון שהגיד שוב
אינו חוזר ומגיד. keivan shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid. It says once
you bear testimony, it's based on the לשון lashon of the פסוק,
pasuk, ואם לא יגיד ונשא עוונו. ve'im lo yagid venasa avono. So
it's all about that original testimony. Once you've testified you cannot retract
your testimony. Okay. So we can't. This is very interesting, right? At
what stage can certain testimony be recanted? Right? In secular law you
can recant it as long as the trial isn't over, right? But
once the judgment is issued, right, then you're, you know, then even
if you recant, you know, it doesn't mean they're going to reopen
the case. Okay. But in הלכה, halacha, as soon as you step
down off that witness stand—they don't have a witness stand—but as soon
as you're done and it's no longer תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei
dibbur and your testimony has been heard, then you cannot retract and
recant your testimony. So basically saying, so no, you're wrong. Even though
they're two people and even though they're saying that they had no
choice or a gun was to their head, they're not believed. If
we have a valid שטר shtar independent of them, we have their
testimony, they're not believed to recant their earlier testimony. כיון שהגיד שוב
אינו חוזר ומגיד. keivan shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid. וכי תימא הני
מילי על פה. vechi teima hanei mili al peh. One minute. That's
when you're dealing that the original testimony was a real testimony, it
was oral testimony offered in court. אבל בשטר לא, aval beshtar lo,
but if it's in a document, maybe that's not the same degree
of real testimony and therefore maybe an oral testimony of the people
themselves standing in front of you and testifying, maybe that should be
weighty enough to outweigh the earlier testimony in the document. Okay, that's
probably, that makes a certain amount of intuitive sense. That's probably what
I would have naturally said. Here they are standing in front of
you saying something. It's not like they gave the earlier testimony directly
in court. So the גמרא Gemara says no. ואמר ריש לקיש, ve'amar
Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, עדים החתומים על השטר נעשה
כמי שנחקרה עדותן בבית דין. edim hachatumim al hashtar na'asa kemi shenichkera
edutan beveit din. That witnesses that are signed on a document, it's
as weighty as oral testimony in court that was validated, okay, and
that was cross-examined. Alright. So actually, which is pretty funny because who's
cross-examining the witnesses before they sign the document? But nevertheless, that's the
legal standing it has. Okay. So now we're saying if the document
has been validated, then they're not believed to say that the loan
didn't take place. That would be recanting their testimony and they wouldn't
be believed if the document had been validated. אלא, ela, so the
גמרא Gemara says you're right. In the end of the משנה, Mishna,
when the document is validated, I don't care what you say, you
are not believed even though you're witnesses because it would be considered
a retraction of an earlier testimony once the document has been independently
validated. So we're going to go back to the first part of
the משנה. Mishna. כי אתמר ארישא אתמר. ki itmar areisha itmar. It's
going back to the first part where it was not independently validated.
הרי אלו נאמנים. harei elu ne'emanim. If they basically are the ones
that validate and say, but we were minors or we were relatives
or we were forced to sign it. So now they're the ones
validating it. הרי אלו נאמנים. harei elu ne'emanim. So and therefore they're
believed. אמר רמי בר חמא, amar Rami bar Chama, on this רמי
בר חמא Rami bar Chama says, לא שנו אלא שאמרו אנוסים היינו
מחמת נפשות. lo shanu ela she'amru anusim hayinu machmat nefashot. When is
that, that their second part of their statement neutralizes the first part?
If they say we were forced because the guy had a gun
to our head. אבל אמרו אנוסים היינו מחמת ממון. aval amru anusim
hayinu machmat mamon. If they say that yes it's our signatures but
we signed it falsely and the reason we signed falsely was he
threatened to burn our house down. אין נאמנים. ein ne'emanim. Then actually
they're not believed the second part of the statement. They validate the
שטר shtar and the second part of their statement is thrown out.
Why is the second part of the statement thrown out? מאי טעמא?
mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אין אדם משים עצמו רשע. ein adam
mesim atzmo rasha. A person is not believed to make themselves a
רשע. rasha. And when you say that you testified falsely because the
guy threatened to burn your house down, you're saying that you transgressed
a biblical prohibition of testifying falsely and we're not prepared, we don't
accept... accept that testimony in court. Now it's interesting, if I say
I signed and I was a relative or I signed and I
was a minor, even though that is basically also invalid testimony, it's
invalid testimony but it's not false testimony. Okay? And therefore you're not
making yourself a רשע. rasha. But in the final case you're making
yourself a רשע. rasha. So here it's very interesting, right? It's basically
and this gets back to the question whether פה שאסר peh she'asar
means you've neutralized your statement and you've said nothing, or does it
mean we've accepted both parts of the statement? And here you see
the difference because what he's saying is no, he's saying you've accept
that basically you want us to accept both parts of your statement.
So first you say you validated the שטר, shtar, first you said
it's your signatures, thank you for validating the שטר, shtar, we believe
that. Now we're totally prepared to believe the second part of your
statement because we believe the first part. But then you went ahead
and you told us that you're a רשע. rasha. So technically we
can't admit that statement into court. Okay so even though we would
be prepared to believe it, that statement cannot be it cannot be
cannot be admitted into court into into into evidence right? And therefore
we're left with just the first part of your statement. Okay, so
so that's the structure of what he's saying. And again I know
it seems a little weird because you've basically neutralized your testimony but
this gets us to the idea of פה שאסר. peh she'asar. Is
פה שאסר peh she'asar that the two parts of your statement have
neutralized one another so just ignore everything I've just said? Or is
פה שאסר peh she'asar if you believe the first part and believe
the second part? And if it's believe the first part and the
second part, sometimes after I believe the first part it triggers something
that doesn't allow me to believe the second part or there's some
other technical reason that the second part of the statement can't be
admitted into testimony. And here the reason is אין אדם משים עצמו
רשע. ein adam meisim atzmo rasha. Meaning that we will not give
legal force to a statement that incriminates yourself. Exactly. Now תוספות Tosafot
asks the question which is Michael has sort of brought up which
is whatever happened to פלגינן דיבורא. palginan dibura. Whatever happened to the
idea that we'll accept the part of your statement that neutralizes the
שטר shtar but we won't accept the part of your statement that
actually says that you're a רשע. rasha. Okay, the רשע rasha part
we'll ignore but we'll accept the power of the statement in terms
of the validity of the שטר. shtar. So תוספות Tosafot discusses that,
that gets us into a whole פלגינן דיבורא palginan dibura statement. For
now, you can read תוספות Tosafot if you want to see it,
for now the basic point is we can't accept that part of
that statement because it makes you a רשע. rasha. Okay so אין
אדם משים עצמו רשע. ein adam meisim atzmo rasha. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: Wait why does it make him
a רשע? rasha? It's a financial consideration. Because you're saying that you
testified falsely and and what and what pressured you to testify falsely
was the threat of losing money, of financial loss. And that is
not that would still be considered a violation of the biblical prohibition.
That's not a legitimate you're supposed to suffer that threat. Okay now
of course you and I might say look maybe halachically I was
supposed to and I did the wrong thing and technically and I
was over on the לאו lav but am I really a רשע?
rasha? Like there were extenuating circumstances. So I'm not saying I didn't
transgress but I'm saying like I wasn't a מזיד, mazid, I was
pressured into it. That should be like I don't know a שוגג
shogeg at least, right? So that is true, but bottom line is
is that is that nevertheless I mean so that's a good question.
Okay? Does that mean that even if you're over on שוגג shogeg
you're invalid? Does it mean the גמרא Gemara is not prepared to
to look at it through that lens? But bottom line is is
that as opposed to if the guy had a gun to your
head where we'd say you didn't transgress at all, here we're saying
you transgressed even if you were compelled, even if you were pressured.
Yes. In comparison to this person who was
compelled and is a רשע, rasha, what's
the status of the קטן katan and the relative? What how do
we... So that's what I was saying, the קטן katan and the
relative basically are saying that they shouldn't have signed either and they
actually their testimony was invalid but they're not but it's not false.
Okay? So they're admitting that the transaction actually took place. Exactly. In
the case of the minor and the relative the transaction took place.
They're just saying our testimony was invalid. So they're invalid witnesses but
they're not but they are not false witnesses. So does the שטר
shtar require עדים edim or not? Yes. Although validity exactly. Now the
question would be let's just take a minute to talk about that
because it's going to be relevant throughout the גמרא, Gemara, who needs
the שטר? shtar? Okay fine, you said that the loan took place
but you are a קטן katan so it's not a valid signature.
But but okay but the loan still took place so what's the
difference? So here's the difference because without a שטר shtar number one
I don't have a lien on property, I only have a lien
because I have a valid שטר shtar number one. Number two without
a שטר shtar you the other guy is believed to say he
paid it off like we just learned. If it's a valid שטר
shtar he's not believed to say he paid it off without proof.
And number three if the שטר shtar is not just evidence that
there was a loan, sometimes a שטר shtar is actually an instrument
like the שטר shtar actually effects the transaction of the sale of
real estate. So if it's not a valid שטר shtar even if
I was trying to sell you the land I didn't actually sell
you the land because you need a valid שטר shtar to effect
the transaction. So you're absolutely correct in the case of the קטנים
ketanim and the relatives A, they're not רשעים reshaim because they're not
saying they testified falsely and B, they're just... saying that the שטר
shtar is invalid. Maybe actually the other things actually occurred but the
שטר shtar remains an invalid שטר. shtar. עדים edim who used to
say, yes, this is my signature on the שטר shtar and I
was there, there was a loan, but like I never read the
שטר, shtar, he didn't borrow $300, he only borrowed $100. Yeah, so
we'll get to some—I mean, that would be similar, but I mean,
that would be a similar case about this, and then I don't
know, okay, I'd have to process it. Let's just read one more
line of the גמרא, Gemara, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, אין נאמנים לפוסלו, ein ne'emanim le-foslo, דברי
רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, וחכמים אומרים נאמנים. va-Chachamim omrim ne'emanim. So
now actually we introduce a new idea of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't buy the הפה שאסר, ha-peh she-asar, even
in the case of the קטנים ketanim and the relatives. Even if
you're the ones that validate the document, you're not believed to say,
yes, it's my signature, but I was a minor, yes, it's my
signature, but I was a relative. Why not? Didn't you completely neutralize
your statement by the second part? And you're not saying you were
a רשע. rasha. So בשלמא לרבנן bishlama le-rabbanan כי טעמייהו, ki tamayehu,
we understand why the rabbis say you neutralize your own statement, שהפה
שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר. she-ha-peh she-asar hu ha-peh she-hitir. אלא לרבי מאיר
מאי טעמא? ella le-Rabbi Meir mai ta'ama? Why according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir are you not believed to neutralize your own statement? בשלמא
פסולי עדות, bishlama pesulei edut, מלווה גופיה מידק דייק ומכתב. malveh gufeih
meidak dayyek u-michtav. We get the case where the guys—where they were
saying that they were, that they were, you know, relatives, because we
basically say you're saying you're relatives, but again, this is the idea
that if we accept both parts, once we accept the first part,
we've triggered something. So we now validated the document. So now we
have a document that basically is a valid document, and we're supposed
to believe that actually it was signed by invalid witnesses? So no,
because we have a חזקה chazakah that a guy who's bothering to
get a document written and to protect his interest is going to
make sure that the witnesses are valid witnesses. So therefore, your claim
now that you're invalid witnesses is against our חזקה chazakah that people
make sure they don't do that, okay? תני נמי, tani nami, and
even if they say they were minors, we were relatives, I mean
by marriage and we're no longer, anyway, כדריש לקיש. ki-d'Resh Lakish. So
and when they say they're minors, we also don't believe it. Why?
דאמר ריש לקיש חזקה אין העדים חותמים על השטר אלא אם כן
נעשה בגדול. de-amar Resh Lakish chazakah ein ha-edim chotmim al ha-shtar ella
im ken na'asah be-gadol. The same basic point: we assume that no,
minors don't sign a document. אלא אנוסים מאי טעמא? ella anusim mai
ta'ama? Why are they not believed to say that they were forced?
Because actually sometimes people do hold guns to their head—people's heads, right?
So if—and we don't—if they're just saying minors or, you know, or
relatives, we say that doesn't happen, minors and relatives don't sign documents.
But how come we don't believe them when they say that they
were forced? So we're going to find out the answer to that
tomorrow, but I just want to remind—but I just want to tell
us, remind you the following, that again, this is the issue of
הפה שאסר. ha-peh she-asar. If all you said that הפה שאסר ha-peh
she-asar did was you've neutralized your own statement, so then רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir should agree. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is actually saying we
don't say הפה שאסר. ha-peh she-asar. The first part of your statement
you validated, the second part of your statement we don't accept. Why
don't we accept? Because against your claim that we're prepared to believe
in theory, against your claim that you were minors or invalid witnesses,
we have our presumptions that minors and invalid witnesses don't sign שטרות,
shtarot, and therefore that neutralizes the second part of your claim, and
only the first part of your claim gets accepted, not the second.
So הפה שאסר ha-peh she-asar means we're prepared to believe the second
part of your claim, okay? We'll give it a certain degree of
believability, but there are other things that could outweigh it, and these
presumptions outweigh it, and only the first part of your claim gets
registered, okay? More about this tomorrow. According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
yeah. We presume that minors don't.